<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Last&#39;s Anatomy 9th Edition on John&#39;s Secret Library</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Last&#39;s Anatomy 9th Edition on John&#39;s Secret Library</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/01.-introduction-to-regional-anatomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/01.-introduction-to-regional-anatomy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The body is composed of four basic tissues—epithelium, connective tissue, muscle and nerve—and every part of the body that is examined with either the naked eye or the microscope can only be made up of one or more of these four elements. There are, of course, different kinds of these tissues depending on the differing functional requirements of the various organs and parts of the body, and the details of cell types and intercellular substances are dealt with in texts on histology. This chapter brings together some notes on certain body tissues and structures to form a relevant introduction to regional anatomy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/02.-upper-limb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/02.-upper-limb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-plan&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  General Plan&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#general-plan&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The upper limb of man is built for prehension. The hand is a grasping mechanism, with four fingers flexing against an opposed thumb. The hand is furthermore the main tactile organ, with a rich nerve supply, particularly of the flexor compartment (p. 22).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In grasping, the thumb is equal in functional value to the other four fingers; loss of the thumb is as disabling as loss of all four fingers. In order to be able to grasp in any position, the forearm is provided with a range of 180° of pronation and supination, and at the elbow has a range of flexion and extension of a like amount. In addition, very free mobility is provided at the shoulder joint, and this mobility is further increased by the mobility of the pectoral girdle through which the upper limb articulates with the axial skeleton.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/03.-lower-limb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/03.-lower-limb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-plan&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  General Plan&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#general-plan&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The human lower limb is built for support and propulsion. The two hip bones (pelvic girdle, p. 53) articulate with one another in front at the pubic symphysis, and each is firmly fixed to the lateral part of the sacrum by the relatively immobile sacroiliac joint. The rigid bony pelvis thus produced transmits the body weight through the acetabulum of the hip bone to the lower limb and likewise transmits the propulsive thrust of the lower limb to the hip bone. In sitting, body weight is transmitted to the ischial tuberosities and the legs are free to rest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/04.-thorax/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/04.-thorax/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Though very different functionally, the wall of the thorax and the wall of the abdomen are one, topographically and developmentally. The essential difference being the presence of ribs in the part primarily concerned with respiration. Many features can be considered together.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;skin-and-subcutaneous-tissue&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  Skin and Subcutaneous Tissue&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#skin-and-subcutaneous-tissue&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The skin varies in texture, tending to be thin in front and thick behind. Distribution of hair varies with sex, age, and race. Natural tension lines of the skin are very constant, and are of tremendous importance to the cosmetic appearance of healed incisions. An incision along a tension line will heal as a hairline scar, virtually invisible; an incision across the lines will tend to heal with either a wide or a heaped-up scar. The tension lines run almost horizontally around the body wall (Fig. 1.2, p. 3).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/05.-abdomen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/05.-abdomen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The skin and subcutaneous tissues of the anterior abdominal wall have been dealt with as part of the body wall (p. 241). To facilitate the clinical description of pain, swellings, etc., the abdomen is divided into areas or regions that are defined by lines on the surface of the anterior abdominal wall. The simplest method is to divide it into four quadrants by vertical and transverse lines through the umbilicus, but usually nine regions are delineated by two vertical and two horizontal lines (Fig. 5.1). The vertical line on each side corresponds to the midclavicular line; when extended downwards it reaches the midinguinal point, which is on the inguinal ligament midway between the pubic symphysis and the anterior superior iliac spine. The lower transverse line is drawn between the tubercles of the iliac crests (intertubercular plane) and the upper transverse line is in the transpyloric plane (p. 312), midway between the jugular notch and the top of the pubic symphysis (although some clinicians use the subcostal plane which is a little lower - level with the lowest part of the costal margin). Using these four lines, three central regions are defined from above downwards: epigastric, umbilical and hypogastric (or suprapubic). Similarly there are three lateral regions on each side: hypochondrial, lumbar and iliac.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/06.-head-neck-and-spine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/06.-head-neck-and-spine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;head-neck-and-spine&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  Head, Neck, and Spine&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#head-neck-and-spine&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first thoracic vertebra lies at the highest part of the sloping thoracic inlet. From its upper border rises the cervical spinal column, gently convex forwards, and supporting the skull. A mass of extensor musculature lies behind the vertebrae. It is supplied segmentally by posterior rami and supports the cervical spine and head. A much smaller amount of prevertebral flexor musculature lies in front of the vertebrae and, more laterally, is attached to the thoracic inlet and the scapula. It is supplied segmentally by anterior rami. This musculature comprises longus colli, rectus capitis anterior and rectus capitis lateralis, longus capitis, scalenus anterior, scalenus medius, scalenus posterior and levator scapulae. The whole mass, projecting but little in front of the cervical spine, lies flat from side to side behind the pharynx, and from here curves away posteriorly; it is covered over by the prevertebral fascia, which thus forms a vertical sheet passing from side to side across the central part of the neck.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/07.-central-nervous-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/docs/lasts/07.-central-nervous-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-central-nervous-system&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;  The Central Nervous System&#xD;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-central-nervous-system&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The central nervous system consists of the brain and spinal cord (spinal medulla). Developmentally, the brain consists of the forebrain, midbrain, and hindbrain. The forebrain is composed of the cerebrum (the two cerebral hemispheres, each with a cavity, the lateral ventricle), and a deeper central portion, the diencephalon, whose main parts are the thalamus and hypothalamus and whose cavity is the third ventricle. Despite this academic distinction between parts, each half of the forebrain is commonly called simply the cerebral hemisphere. The midbrain is a small region whose cavity is the aqueduct and which connects the forebrain with the hindbrain, consisting of the pons, medulla oblongata, and cerebellum and whose cavity is the fourth ventricle. The midbrain, pons, and medulla collectively form the brainstem. All parts of the brain are contained within the cranial cavity; the medulla passes through the foramen magnum of the skull and changes its name to spinal cord where the first cervical nerve roots emerge. Cerebrospinal fluid is produced by the choroid plexuses within parts of the ventricles; its only exit is through foramina in the roof of the fourth ventricle, in the medulla.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
